<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true description of the passion of our Sauiour Iesus Christ as it was acted by the bloodie Iewes: and registred by the blessed Euangelists. In English meetre by Iohn Bullokar, Calend. Nouemb. 1618.</title>
            <author>J. B. (John Bullokar)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 46 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17231</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4085</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117069</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852284</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852284</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17600</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17231)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17600)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1129:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true description of the passion of our Sauiour Iesus Christ as it was acted by the bloodie Iewes: and registred by the blessed Euangelists. In English meetre by Iohn Bullokar, Calend. Nouemb. 1618.</title>
                  <author>J. B. (John Bullokar)</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Purslowe, for Samuel Rand, and are to be sold at his shop neere Holburne Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B C⁴ (-A1, C4, blanks?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Passion --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A true</hi> DESCRIPTION OF THE PASSION OF OVR SAVIOVR IESVS
CHRIST: As it was acted by the bloodie Iewes: And regiſtred by the
bleſſed <hi>Euangeliſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In Engliſh Meetre by IOHN BVLLOKAR, <hi>Calend. Nouemb.</hi>
1618.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>George Purſlowe,</hi> for <hi>Samuel</hi>
Rand, <hi>and are to be ſold at his ſhop neere</hi> Holburne Bridge.
1622.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A true DESCRIPTION of our <hi>Sauiours</hi> PASSION.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>WRapt in our ſinfull fleſh, yet free from ſinne,</l>
               <l>The louing-worlds Redeemer lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g had ſought,</l>
               <l>Vnto himſelfe the ſtubborne Iewes to winne,</l>
               <l>With mighty ſignes &amp; wonders daily wrought:</l>
               <l>But wiſhed fruit his zeale could neuer gaine:</l>
               <l>He plowd the ſands, and reapt but loſſe of paine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And when he had full thirty three yeeres ſpace,</l>
               <l>For men, and with men dwelt on earth below,</l>
               <l>Lending rich treaſures of his heauenly grace,</l>
               <l>To pay thoſe countleſſe debts that Sinne did owe.</l>
               <l>The time was come, that ſhould our God reſtore</l>
               <l>To heauen aboue, from whence he came before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whoſe paſſage muſt by Death prepared be,</l>
               <l>(As erſt the holy Prophets had foretold)</l>
               <l>That ſo his death from death might ſet vs free,</l>
               <l>Whom ſinne from life, as ſlaues to death had ſold.</l>
               <l>So deadly was the diuelliſh Serpents ſting,</l>
               <l>That nought but Gods death, life to man could bring.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Which to aſſure vs, ere he parted hence,</l>
               <l>He leaues behind for our immortall good,</l>
               <l>A full releaſe of <hi>Adams</hi> firſt offence,</l>
               <l>Scaling the Charter with his deareſt blood:</l>
               <l>That man might ſee his loue, and learne thereby,</l>
               <l>To loath the ſinne that made a God to die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet neuer could the powerfull ſtroke of death,</l>
               <l>Nor Fate, nor Chance, nor Satans ſecret blow,</l>
               <l>Nor humane force enforce him yeeld his breath,</l>
               <l>Vntill his Will gaue leaue it ſhould be ſo:</l>
               <l>The Iewes might rage, yet heauen had fore decreed,</l>
               <l>He choſe to die, though they did act the deed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But leſt the ſudden ſtorme, if vnforetold,</l>
               <l>Should drowne the ſeeds of Faith ſo lately ſowne,</l>
               <l>Or make new kindled loue of him grow cold,</l>
               <l>In weak conceits not to perfection growne:</l>
               <l>He ſhewes them euery thing muſt come to paſſe,</l>
               <l>That of him in the Scripture written was.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And knowing that the houre approched now,</l>
               <l>To his ſmall number of Diſciples, he</l>
               <l>Plamely foretels his death<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and manner how:</l>
               <l>Withall, the time when as his death ſhould be,</l>
               <l>To ſtrength their doubtfull thoughts, &amp; make thé
know,</l>
               <l>He could foreſee, though would not ſhun the blow.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Two dayes there are (ſaith he) and then the Feaſt</l>
               <l>Of Eaſter comes, when <hi>Moſes</hi> did command,</l>
               <l>In memory that Iſrael was releaſt</l>
               <l>From hard oppreſſion of proud Egypt land,</l>
               <l>The Paſchall lambe ſhould yeerely eaten be,</l>
               <l>Of all their ſeed, whom God had Io ſet free.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now the old Lawes end approcheth nie,</l>
               <l>Theſe ſhadowing Figures ſhortly muſt away:</l>
               <l>The Sonne of man ſhall be betraid to die,</l>
               <l>And on the Croſſe the worlds great ranſome pay,</l>
               <l>To free it from infernall <hi>Charons</hi> power,</l>
               <l>Whoſe tyrant rage would life and ſoule deuoure.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus hauing warn'd, whilſt at Bethania he,</l>
               <l>Receiu'd in <hi>Simons</hi> houſe, doth there remaine,</l>
               <l>A woman by him late from ſinne ſet free,</l>
               <l>Doth come her louing Lord to entertaine;</l>
               <l>Bringing a boxe of Alabaſter faire,</l>
               <l>Fill'd with an oyntment, coſtly, ſweet, and rare,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O Loue! ſole life of Peace, and death of Strife:</l>
               <l>Strong knot to tye: ſweet vnion of conſent:</l>
               <l>Thoughts purity: faire Mappe of Angels life:</l>
               <l>Heauens new-made Liuery: Nurce of all content:</l>
               <l>How true it is the world of thee doth ſay?</l>
               <l>That whoſo loues, can brooke no long delay.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The curious Boxe ſhe breaks, and quickly powres</l>
               <l>This precious liquor on her Sauiours head;</l>
               <l>Whoſe ſweet diſtilling drops full mainly ſhowres</l>
               <l>Adowne his necke, and on his garments ſhed,</l>
               <l>Refining all the ayre neere which they fell,</l>
               <l>With fragrant odour of their pleaſing ſmell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But enuious Malice ſoone occaſion finds,</l>
               <l>This womans godly meaning to reproue:</l>
               <l>Some ſtanders by do murmure in their minds,</l>
               <l>As diſcontent to ſee ſuch zealous loue.</l>
               <l>His owne Diſciples too that ſate at bord,</l>
               <l>Do grudge ſuch coſt beſtowd vpon their Lord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Why need this needleſſe waſte be made (ſay they)</l>
               <l>Of what was worth three hundred pence at leaſt?</l>
               <l>It better had bin ſold, and giuen away</l>
               <l>To poore for almes, againſt this holy Feaſt:</l>
               <l>'Tis pitie ſuch ſweet oyle ſo dearely bought,</l>
               <l>With idle vaine expence ſhould come to nought.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus they: But Chriſt that ſought to ſaue his foes,</l>
               <l>Forgets not now to helpe a friend at need:</l>
               <l>He ſoone perceiues the grudging thoughts of thoſe,</l>
               <l>That were miſlikers of this womans deed,</l>
               <l>And mildly doth rebuke them for their ſinne,</l>
               <l>With praiſe of her that did the worke begin.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O why ſhould you, whom I haue choſe for mine,</l>
               <l>Againſt your louing Lord offended be?</l>
               <l>Why ſhould your murmuring hearts with ſpite repine</l>
               <l>At her, whoſe faith wrought this good worke on me?</l>
               <l>Take heed, this leſſon firſt was learnt at Hell,</l>
               <l>To grudge at grace, and enuie doing well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The poore may be relieued when you will,</l>
               <l>No want of them the earth doth euer find:</l>
               <l>But me you ſhall not haue amongſt you ſtill:</l>
               <l>The work's now done that heauen had erſt aſſign'd,</l>
               <l>And ſhe that knew I ſhortly hence muſt go,</l>
               <l>Againſt my buriall did this coſt beſtow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Of truth therefore I ſay, in each place where</l>
               <l>The worlds Redemption ſhalbe preacht or taught,</l>
               <l>This womans zeale ſhall be related there,</l>
               <l>In memory of what ſhe now hath wrought.</l>
               <l>Great loue ſhall ſurely reape a great reward:</l>
               <l>Heauen do's the hart, not outward ſhews regard.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By this, the Prieſts and Scribes, whoſe hearts were
ſet</l>
               <l>A fire with burning ſpite, and deadly hate,</l>
               <l>At <hi>Caiaphas</hi> palace are together met,</l>
               <l>In councell cloſely to deliberate,</l>
               <l>How they might Ieſus take by ſubtill traine,</l>
               <l>And with ſome ſhew of Iuſtice haue him ſlaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet muſt we not (ſay they) in any wiſe,</l>
               <l>At this great Feaſt, in ſuch a courſe proceed,</l>
               <l>Left the rude people ſhould againſt vs riſe,</l>
               <l>Or ſtir rebellion to withſtand the deed:</l>
               <l>His words, his workes, and doctrine haue bin ſuch,</l>
               <l>That him as now we cannot ſafely touch.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But Sathan fearing, leſt by this delay,</l>
               <l>His long-deſired worke ſhould reſt vnwrought,</l>
               <l>Preſents them with an vnexpected way,</l>
               <l>Wherby their miſchiefe might to paſſe be brought,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iudas</hi> one of the Twelue, whom Chriſt had choſe,</l>
               <l>(Vnhappy wretch) to this aſſembly goes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>There doth the Traitour ſet his Lord to ſale,</l>
               <l>Mongſt thoſe he knew long ſought to ſucke his blood:</l>
               <l>Whoſe precious worth this caitiffe counts ſo ſmall,</l>
               <l>He bids them make the price as they thought good:</l>
               <l>What will you giue me, (thus doth <hi>Iudas</hi> ſay)</l>
               <l>And I into your hands will him betray?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O bleſſed Lady! hadſt thou preſent beene,</l>
               <l>When thus thy Sonne by theeuiſh hands was ſold</l>
               <l>To bloody Merchants, it had ſoone beene ſeene,</l>
               <l>How deare true owners wel-got pearles do hold:</l>
               <l>Thy tender loue had pitcht the price ſo hie,</l>
               <l>That Iewiſh wealth one haire ſhould neuer buy.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But thou true picture of pure piety,</l>
               <l>Reſignſt to heauens decree thy proper right,</l>
               <l>Suffering a damned wretch contemptuouſly,</l>
               <l>To make a market of thy dearſt delight:</l>
               <l>Then hie thee, hie thee, ſince the caſe ſo ſtands,</l>
               <l>Come buy thine own fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe Prieſts murthring hands.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And <hi>Iudas,</hi> O if greedy hope of gaine</l>
               <l>Entice thee thus thy Sauiour to forgo,</l>
               <l>Why doſt thou ſhew thy ſelfe ſo fondly vaine,</l>
               <l>As offer him to thoſe that hate him ſo?</l>
               <l>His friends (I wis) would giue more mony for him,</l>
               <l>Then ſcornfull foes, whoſe pride and ſpite abhor him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O what would <hi>Lazarus,</hi> new brought to liue</l>
               <l>From graue, haue payd to keep his Lord from death?</l>
               <l>What price would <hi>Magdalen</hi> refuſe to giue,</l>
               <l>That lou'd her Maſter dearer then her breath?</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Martha,</hi> and his Virgin-mother too,</l>
               <l>That lou'd him more then all the world can do</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yea leaue the earth, and aske of Angels bright,</l>
               <l>What they would giue thee for their King diuine?</l>
               <l>(Doubtleſſe to get him home) their chiefe delight,</l>
               <l>They would exchange their heauenly ſtate for thine:</l>
               <l>O hadſt thou thus made ſale of Chriſt before,</l>
               <l>Thy guilt had beene the leſſe, and gaine the more.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But Sin with ſelf conceit it ſelfe ſtill blinds,</l>
               <l>Daring, without reſpect of what it may:</l>
               <l>Witneſſe falſe <hi>Iudas,</hi> who with deſperate
mind,</l>
               <l>Tels proudly to the Prieſts, he will betray:</l>
               <l>As if the Maker of heauen, earth, and ſeas,</l>
               <l>Were in his power to vſe him as he pleaſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They glad with others blame t'effect the deed;</l>
               <l>Whereto their proper malice would aſpire,</l>
               <l>Reſolue to proſecute it now with ſpeed,</l>
               <l>And thirty pence appoint him for his hire.</l>
               <l>He ſtraight accepts the wages they aſſign'd:</l>
               <l>Slight gaine ſoone ſets to work a willing mind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah <hi>Iudas,</hi> ſinke of ſinne, and earthly ſhame,</l>
               <l>Firſt luckleſſe lambe that ſtraid from Chriſts deare
fold,</l>
               <l>Monſter of mankind, vile reproach of fame;</l>
               <l>Sequeſtred from all grace, moſt impious bold:</l>
               <l>Blind reprobate (alas) what haſt thou done,</l>
               <l>To buy hel fire with ſale of Gods deere Sonne?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O did thy wretched eyes ſo grieue to ſee,</l>
               <l>Three hundred peniworth of oyle beſtowd,</l>
               <l>Whoſe coſtly value ſhould aduantag'd thee,</l>
               <l>If thy falſe hand had ſold the ſame abroad:</l>
               <l>That now to make amends for ſuch ſhrewd loſſe,</l>
               <l>Thou muſt betray thy Sauiour to the Croſſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Did this bad crop ſpring vp from heauenly ſeed?</l>
               <l>Did Chriſts example ſuch vile thrift maintaine?</l>
               <l>Ah no, he taught thee by his Word and Deed,</l>
               <l>T'abhorre the muddie mind of worldly gaine,</l>
               <l>T'embrace pure thoughts, whoſe ſafety feares no fall,</l>
               <l>To hurt no man, and to do good to all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But thou (vnchang'd) a graceleſſe Impe of hell,</l>
               <l>With <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſpitefull ſonnes, in ſin art
growne;</l>
               <l>Whoſe malice did their brother <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſell</l>
               <l>For twenty pence, to Merchant-men vnknowne:</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Ioſeph</hi> was preferd to honour hie,</l>
               <l>And call'd the Sauiour of the world thereby.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So Chriſt thy Lord, by thee ſold to be ſlaine,</l>
               <l>Though death and hell ſtriue both to preſſe him downe,</l>
               <l>Shall Phoenix-like with glory riſe againe,</l>
               <l>And win by death an euerlaſting Crowne:</l>
               <l>That in his Name, eterniz'd without end,</l>
               <l>All knees in heauen, in earth, in hell may bend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The Feaſt of ſweet bread now was hard at hand,</l>
               <l>And ſpotleſſe paſcall lambes were markt to die:</l>
               <l>When Chriſts Diſciples came to vnderſtand</l>
               <l>Their Maſters will in this Solemnitie:</l>
               <l>Where wilt thou (ſay they) we prepare for thee</l>
               <l>The Paſſeouer, that now muſt eaten be?</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Straight bleſſed <hi>Peter</hi> readieſt to obay,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Iohn,</hi> whom Ieſus alwaies held moſt deare,</l>
               <l>Are called for, and ſent without delay,</l>
               <l>To make prouiſion for this heauenly cheare:</l>
               <l>Receiuing by their Lords directing care,</l>
               <l>A ſigne that ſhewd them where they ſhould prepare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>You two (ſaith Chriſt) ſhall now this taske begin</l>
               <l>At yonder towne, where you ſhall ſurely meet</l>
               <l>A man, aſſoone as you are entred in,</l>
               <l>Bearing a pot of water through the ſtreet;</l>
               <l>Him follow, whereſoeuer he doth go,</l>
               <l>What houſe he enters, enter you alſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Aske of the owner for ſome place, where I,</l>
               <l>With my Diſciples, may this Supper eate;</l>
               <l>And he (I know) will ſhew you by and by,</l>
               <l>A parler roome, well paued, faire and great,</l>
               <l>Which will be fit: make ready there for me,</l>
               <l>For there ſhall this laſt Supper eaten be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O happy Feaſt held by a heauenly King,</l>
               <l>Where bread of life with bounty was beſtowd:</l>
               <l>No more a Type, but now a figured thing,</l>
               <l>True Rocke, whence pure ſin-cleanſing waters flowd:</l>
               <l>Sweet antidote, whoſe vertue ſets man free,</l>
               <l>From deadly ſurfet of forbidden tree.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>When thou wert made, each ceremonious Rite,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat had prefigur'd
better things to come,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Gods appointment
was aboliſht quite;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ew Sacraments
ſucceeding in their roome:</l>
               <l>Whoſe worth in Chriſt who worthily embrace,</l>
               <l>Adopted are new heires of heauenly grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Cleare light was then in place of ſhadowes brought:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igures for better
Truth exchang'd away:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he ioyfull Goſpel
for the Law was taught;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd Mercy crownd,
where Iuſtice earſt bare ſway:</l>
               <l>New Life was borne, and Death began to die,</l>
               <l>In this great Suppers heauenly myſterie.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here did the King of
Glory thinke no ſcorne,</l>
               <l>Leauing behind a patterne for vs meet)</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith girded loynes
addreſt in ſeruile forme,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſtoope and
waſh his owne Diſciples feet:</l>
               <l>That thoſe which after ſhould the Goſpel preach,</l>
               <l>Might by himſelfe be cleans'd, ere they did teach.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t this is not yet
all that then was done:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or the
new-ſpouſed Church redeemd ſo deere,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he precious Body of
Gods only Sonne,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as inſtituted to
be eaten heere:</l>
               <l>That bleſſed Body borne for ſinners good,</l>
               <l>True Manna, farre exceeding Angels food.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Such wiſedome did th'Almighty workman ſhow,</l>
               <l>In altering ſhadowes into ſubſtance true:</l>
               <l>Such humble ſeruice did a God beſtow,</l>
               <l>Pure humbled thoughts in proud man to renue:</l>
               <l>Such precious cates were by our dying Lord,</l>
               <l>Bequeath'd for euer to this heauenly boord.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The bright Sunne now with Weſterne clouds was hid:</l>
               <l>Dim darkneſſe on the errth began to grow;</l>
               <l>Nor day, nor night it was, when Ieſus did</l>
               <l>With his Diſciples to this Supper go.</l>
               <l>And as they ate, he ſpake: Of truth I ſay,</l>
               <l>That one amongſt you here ſhall me betray:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>They ſtraight with dead pale lookes bewray their feare,</l>
               <l>And gaze together, doubtfull to ſuſpect:</l>
               <l>As mazed perſons wonted are, that heare</l>
               <l>A ſudden preſage of ſome dire effect:</l>
               <l>And willing there their innocence to trie,</l>
               <l>Each after other ſaid: Lord, is it I?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iudas</hi> that felt himſelfe neere toucht herein,</l>
               <l>Wondring to heare his guilt ſo ſoone made knowne;</l>
               <l>And fearing, ſilence might diſcloſe the ſinne:</l>
               <l>(For Craft and Treaſon ſtill are linkt in one)</l>
               <l>Askt laſt of all, faining himſelfe diſmaid,</l>
               <l>Lord, is it I? Chriſt anſwered, Thou haſt ſaid.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But wo be vnto him that makes this match;</l>
               <l>Selling the Sonne of man to ſinners ſpite:</l>
               <l>Farre better had it bin for that vile wretch,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f he, vnborne, had
neuer ſeene the light.</l>
               <l>O ten times happy life, that liueth well!</l>
               <l>But curſt is he that liues, to liue in hell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Theſe threats in <hi>Iudas</hi> could breed no remorce,</l>
               <l>That blacke deteſted action to abiure.</l>
               <l>Obdurat harts, though warn'd, yet ſtil wax worſe:</l>
               <l>Like rotten vlcers maſtring Phyſickes cure.</l>
               <l>So hard it is, except Gods grace be ſtrong,</l>
               <l>To ſaue that ſoule where ſin hath harbord lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Peter,</hi> whoſe daunted thoughts could take no
reſt,</l>
               <l>Vntill the author of this ill were knowne,</l>
               <l>Makes ſignes to <hi>Iohn,</hi> who lean'd on Ieſus
breſt,</l>
               <l>To aske his name, whoſe ſin ſhould cauſe their mone.</l>
               <l>Reſoluing boldly, if in him it lay,</l>
               <l>To kill the wretch did plot his Lords decay.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But <hi>Peters</hi> purpoſe could not come to paſſe:</l>
               <l>The hatefull traitor cloſely ſits conceal'd:</l>
               <l>In ſecret <hi>Iohn</hi> demandeth who it was,</l>
               <l>And Chriſt in ſecret thus to him reueal'd:</l>
               <l>Who next receiues a dipped ſop of me,</l>
               <l>Shall do the deed, the reſt hereof are free.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O <hi>Iohn,</hi> dearſt darling of thy dying Lord!</l>
               <l>Earths flower, heauens ſtarre, pure virgin, foe to luſt:</l>
               <l>What pen can worthily thy praiſe record,</l>
               <l>Or blaze thy bleſſed name with titles iuſt,</l>
               <l>That foundſt ſuch grace to aske and vnderſtand,</l>
               <l>When none of all thy fellowes durſt demand?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Soone after in the diſh Chriſt dips a ſop,</l>
               <l>And gaue it mildly to his murthering foe;</l>
               <l>Who vnrelenting takes and eates it vp:</l>
               <l>But ſtraight the diuell entred in him tho;</l>
               <l>Vrging his traiterous heart ſtill more and more,</l>
               <l>To execute what he had vowd before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>That which thou doſt (ſaith Chriſt) with ſpeed
fulfill:</l>
               <l>Not animating him to do the deed:</l>
               <l>But ſhewing by theſe words, the great good will</l>
               <l>He had, that mans ſaluation ſhould proceed:</l>
               <l>For which abſented from his Fathers ſight,</l>
               <l>His loue thinkes long till it be finiſht quite.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Whereto theſe words were ſpoke, none then did know,</l>
               <l>Onely (perhaps) falſe <hi>Iudas</hi> vnderſtood:</l>
               <l>They thought Chriſt bade him buy, and to beſtow</l>
               <l>Some thing in almes, to do poore people good,</l>
               <l>Or for the Feaſt prouide: thus Error too</l>
               <l>Helpes forward what this Traitor meanes to do.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But ſee how apt mans frailty is to ſinne,</l>
               <l>When humbled thoughts with pride are ouerthrowne?</l>
               <l>Theſe late-amaz'd Diſciples now begin,</l>
               <l>(Forgetting quite Chriſts laſt example ſhowne)</l>
               <l>To reaſon hard in words, and diſagree,</l>
               <l>Who ſhould among themſelues the greateſt be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah fondlings! is your Maſter cumbred now</l>
               <l>With humane error of his dying day?</l>
               <l>Hath one amongſt your ſelues conſpired how,</l>
               <l>By trecherie, to take his life away?</l>
               <l>And can you, warnd hereof, mis-ſpend your time,</l>
               <l>In idle folly of ambitious crime?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O plucke vp ſinne whilſt yet the root is young:</l>
               <l>Surceaſe this variance, breeding but offence:</l>
               <l>Weepe your owne loſſe, waile your Redeemers wrong,</l>
               <l>And wiſh to die with him in innocence:</l>
               <l>Rather then ſtriue to be exalted hier,</l>
               <l>As pamperd worldlings, in their pride, deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But Chriſt orecome with that exceeding loue,</l>
               <l>Which from the world had choſe them for his owne,</l>
               <l>Surpreſt with griefe, forbearing to reproue</l>
               <l>This folly, and defect of duty ſhowne:</l>
               <l>Yet to make knowne their faults, and ſtrife appeaſe,</l>
               <l>He gently warnes them in like words to theſe:</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Supremacie and honour is embrac't</l>
               <l>Of profane Potentates, and earthly kings;</l>
               <l>Not worthy thoſe deſires whoſe thoughts are plac't</l>
               <l>On better loue of God, and heauenly things:</l>
               <l>For ſuch, though greateſt, muſt inferiour be,</l>
               <l>And miniſter to thoſe of low degree.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The maſter who doth ſit at meat alone,</l>
               <l>Exceeds the ſeruant that attends his will:</l>
               <l>Yet you to me this duty haue not ſhowne,</l>
               <l>For I do miniſter among you ſtill:</l>
               <l>And by humility example giue,</l>
               <l>How ſuch as are my followers ought to liue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But you for my ſake haue abandon'd cleane</l>
               <l>The late-lou'd world, renounc't your ſelues and all,</l>
               <l>And in my greatſt temptations alwayes been,</l>
               <l>Abiding with me ſince I did you call:</l>
               <l>And therefore I appointed haue for ye,</l>
               <l>As God my Father doth appoint for me:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I meane a Kingdome, not of earthly bliſſe,</l>
               <l>Such as mortality aſpires to get:</l>
               <l>But one in heauen that perpetuall is;</l>
               <l>Where, at my table you ſhall drinke and eate:</l>
               <l>Where you ſhall ſit on ſeates, as is decreed,</l>
               <l>Iudging the twelue great Tribes of Iſraels ſeed.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>So ſpake our Lord, when from the table roſe</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iudas,</hi> full fraught with hel-nurc't deſperate
ſinne,</l>
               <l>And haſtily out of the houſe he goes,</l>
               <l>Leauing his Maſter and the reſt within,</l>
               <l>True type of heauenly bliſſe at latter day,</l>
               <l>When no bad bides, nor good doth go away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And now doth Chriſt in ſweeteſt ſpeech commend</l>
               <l>His loue, and mutuall concord to the reſt,</l>
               <l>With promiſe, that he would from heauen ſend</l>
               <l>Another Comforter to make them bleſt:</l>
               <l>Whoſe preſence ſhould abide for euermore,</l>
               <l>And teach them all the truth they heard before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His peace likewiſe he doth among them leaue,</l>
               <l>Exhorting perfect vnity in one,</l>
               <l>A growing: branches from the Vine receiue</l>
               <l>Their fruit, and beare not of themſelues alone.</l>
               <l>Forewarning too, that troubles, hate, and ſpite,</l>
               <l>Should ſhortly for his Name vpon them light.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Which to indure, without grudge or deſpaire,</l>
               <l>He cheares them vp by his examples ſtill:</l>
               <l>Concluding laſtly with a feruent prayer,</l>
               <l>That God would bleſſe and keepe them from all ill.</l>
               <l>As that together they in one might grow,</l>
               <l>As he himſelfe was with the Father, ſo.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>The night is now farre ſpent, the Supper done;</l>
               <l>The Grace is ſaid, the Table tooke away:</l>
               <l>The Gheſts are riſen, and the worke begun,</l>
               <l>For which the Sonne of God on earth did ſtay:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iudas</hi> is comming with a kiſſe to greet him,</l>
               <l>And with the Eleuen, Chriſt goes forth to meet him.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>A place there is, where (raiſd from lower ground)</l>
               <l>A goodly fruitfull Mountaine threats the skie;</l>
               <l>Whoſe top with Oliue branches ſhadowed round,</l>
               <l>Forbids the heat of heauens bright burning Eye,</l>
               <l>And ouerlookes a garden faire and ſweet,</l>
               <l>Cloſe ſituated to <hi>Gethſeman</hi> ſtreet.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Hither, as was his often former guiſe,</l>
               <l>When he in priuate for his Church would pray,</l>
               <l>Or did his owne Diſciples catechiſe,</l>
               <l>This laſt night our Redeemer tooke his way:</l>
               <l>That ſo he in a Garden might reſtore,</l>
               <l>What <hi>Adam</hi> in a Garden loſt before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And by the way thus warnes: All you this night</l>
               <l>Shall run in ſcandall great becauſe of me:</l>
               <l>For it is written, I will ſurely ſmite</l>
               <l>The Shepheard, and his ſheepe ſhall ſcattered be:</l>
               <l>But when I riſen am from Death below,</l>
               <l>To Galilee before you will I go.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah poore Diſciples, weake and miſerable,</l>
               <l>Now is at hand the comfort-killing houre;</l>
               <l>The houre of feare and darkneſſe palpable,</l>
               <l>Whoſe foggie dampe ſhall in your hearts obſcure</l>
               <l>Bright beames of Faith, and yet lend light to ſee,</l>
               <l>How fraile and feeble of your ſelues you be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In one way now together all do go:</l>
               <l>In diuers (ſhortly) all ſhall ſcattered ſlie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>True faithfull followers now your ſelues you ſhow,</l>
               <l>As ready with your Lord to liue and die.</l>
               <l>Yet danted with baſe feare, you ſhortly ſhall</l>
               <l>Renounce your truth, your faith, your Lord &amp; all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus ſtill freſh cauſe of ſorrow Chriſt doth find,</l>
               <l>His ouer-burdened ſences to diſmay:</l>
               <l>Ere-while he troubled was, to thinke in mind,</l>
               <l>That one of his owne Twelue ſhould him betray:</l>
               <l>And now not one alone, but all the reſt,</l>
               <l>Shall falſe their faith, &amp; leaue their Lord
diſtreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Alas, ſweet Sauiour, who ſhall comfort now,</l>
               <l>The dreadfull terror of this ſad nights feare?</l>
               <l>Thy Father threats the ſword with angry brow,</l>
               <l>Againſt thee, for our ſins, which thou muſt beare.</l>
               <l>Thy mother wails, thy friends ſhal all forſake thee,</l>
               <l>Whilſt death deuiſing foes conſpire to take thee.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O might the merit of thy bitter paines,</l>
               <l>Endur'd for all alike, alike redound</l>
               <l>To all of <hi>Adams</hi> ſonnes, whom death detaines,</l>
               <l>Some conſolation herein would be found:</l>
               <l>But (O deare God!) thou knowſt how few indeed,</l>
               <l>For all theſe torments ſhall the better ſpeed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And to th'increaſing of thy griefes, doſt ſee</l>
               <l>Millions of miſ-beleeuing Soules miſ-led</l>
               <l>With ſinnes ſweet bait, or infidelitie,</l>
               <l>Shall run into perdition void of dread:</l>
               <l>Scorning thy Croſſe and Paſſion ſuffred here,</l>
               <l>Or valuing light what thou haſt bought ſo deare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But <hi>Peter</hi> hearing what his Maſter told,</l>
               <l>And cleare in conſcience from ſo blacke a ſinne,</l>
               <l>Preſuming of his ſtrength with courage bold,</l>
               <l>To promiſe for himſelfe, doth thus begin:</l>
               <l>Though all the world offended were in thee,</l>
               <l>Yet herewith ſpotted <hi>Peter</hi> would not be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O <hi>Simon, Simon,</hi> (thus doth Chriſt reply)</l>
               <l>The ſubtill Fiend your ſetled thoughts to quaile,</l>
               <l>Hath ſought to ſift you all as wheat, but I</l>
               <l>Haue prayd for thee, that thy faith might not faile.</l>
               <l>Thou therefore once turn'd to the perfect way,</l>
               <l>Confirme thy weaker brethren what thou may.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>To whom th'Apoſtle, (growne more confident,)</l>
               <l>Lord, I am ready with reſolued heart,</l>
               <l>Not onely to endure impriſonment,</l>
               <l>Or in ſuch ſlight affliction take thy part,</l>
               <l>But with thee loſe my life, if need require,</l>
               <l>To ſhew my loue, and further thy deſire.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The wakefull Cocke (ſaith Chriſt) twice ſhall not crow</l>
               <l>This night, till thou haſt three times me denide:</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Peter</hi> cannot be perſwaded ſo,</l>
               <l>But plights his faith moſt conſtant to abide:</l>
               <l>At which, the reſt, ſeeing his courage ſuch,</l>
               <l>By ſolemne vow, proteſt to do as much.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O what high taskes can raſhneſſe vndertake,</l>
               <l>Ere difficulty of the worke be knowne?</l>
               <l>What vaunts can ouer-weening humors make,</l>
               <l>Which in an inſtant will he ouerthrowne?</l>
               <l>Great oddes in what they'l do, and what they ſpeake:</l>
               <l>Their words are ſtrong, their deeds will be but weake.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Boldly they boaſt themſelues, reſolu'd to ſlay,</l>
               <l>And die with Chriſt in ſuch a quarrell good:</l>
               <l>Yet one ſmall ſtorme ſhall blow them all away,</l>
               <l>And he for them muſt bide and ſhed his blood.</l>
               <l>So feeble are th'attempts by man begun,</l>
               <l>When heauenly grace is not relide vpon.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>But Chriſt in mercy doth not ſue the debt,</l>
               <l>Which they by vow ſtand bound this night to pay:</l>
               <l>Knowing their weake eſtates vnable yet,</l>
               <l>He well is pleaſd to grant a longer day;</l>
               <l>When after his Aſcenſion they ſhall,</l>
               <l>In vnknowne ſhores be wider ſcattered all.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then ſhall ſelf-penance ſcourge the trothles blame</l>
               <l>Of this nights worke, that now their worke defaces:</l>
               <l>Then ſhall they boldly preach his healthfull Name;</l>
               <l>Not recking danger, or the worlds diſgraces:</l>
               <l>Then ſhall they go to priſons ioyfully,</l>
               <l>And for his Truths ſake glorious Martyrs die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>By this, the Lambe of God, who for mans ſinne,</l>
               <l>With willing ſteps, went meeting to be ſlaine,</l>
               <l>And made a Sacrifice: is entred in</l>
               <l>The Garden with his yet-vnſcattered traine;</l>
               <l>To whom he ſorrowing ſpeakes, Here ſit &amp; ſtay,</l>
               <l>Whilſt I withdraw my ſelfe awhile to pray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then <hi>Peter, Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> he takes
aſide,</l>
               <l>When ſtraight with an exceeding feare oppreſt,</l>
               <l>His ſtoniſht ſences could no longer hide</l>
               <l>The griefe, that had ſurcharg'd his guiltleſſe
breſt.</l>
               <l>My ſoule is heauie to the death, ſaith he,</l>
               <l>Abide you here, and watch awhile with me.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Accompany thy Sauiour, O my Soule,</l>
               <l>In outward ſignes of inward griping wo:</l>
               <l>Breake forth in ſighs, and with true teares condole,</l>
               <l>The dreadfull horror that torments him ſo:</l>
               <l>Sith for thy ſake this ſorrow pierc't his heart,</l>
               <l>Good reaſon in his griefe thou beare ſome part.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>See how that heauenly face is altred quite,</l>
               <l>Scarce to be knowne by what it was euen now:</l>
               <l>Dead-pale vſurpes the ſeat of red and white:</l>
               <l>And Care ſits figur'd in his wrinkled brow.</l>
               <l>Diſtreſſefull feare ſeemes drown'd in watery eyne,</l>
               <l>That ouerwaſh his cheekes with weeping brine:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Like as the bright Sunne in a Welkin faire,</l>
               <l>With pitchie miſt on ſudden ouer-caſt,</l>
               <l>Shoots forth his beames in vaine to cleare the ayer:</l>
               <l>Cloud vpon cloud ſtill thickning wondrous faſt:</l>
               <l>Blacke night doth ouer-hang the ſhadowed land,</l>
               <l>Threatning a cruell tempeſt out of hand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or as the Sea toſt by ſome boiſterous wind,</l>
               <l>Doth mainly beat vpon the quiet ſhore,</l>
               <l>Swels in huge waues aboue due courſe of kind,</l>
               <l>And with ſelfe-motion laboureth more and more:</l>
               <l>Such is the troubled ſtate, and deepe vnreſt,</l>
               <l>Wherewith our Sauiours ſoule is now oppreſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O heauens great'ſt ſtrength, and Angels chiefeſt ioy,</l>
               <l>Earths hope, hels feare, true God omnipotent!</l>
               <l>What griefe can vexe, or terror ſtrange diſmay</l>
               <l>Thy ſpotleſſe ſoule with ſuch ſad
languiſhment?</l>
               <l>What terror can theſe pangs of paſſion breed,</l>
               <l>Which make thee ſeeme not as thou art indeed?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Is death, the entrance to felicity,</l>
               <l>The finall date of all terreſtriall wo,</l>
               <l>The glorious triumph of thy victory,</l>
               <l>The way by which perforce all fleſh muſt go,</l>
               <l>So dreadfull to affright thee, like as thoſe,</l>
               <l>Which here on earth their higheſt bliſſe repoſe?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O wherefore didſt thou leaue thy heauenly Throne,</l>
               <l>And ſhrowd a Godhead in our mortall frame?</l>
               <l>Why haſt thou here by ſignes thy might made knowne,</l>
               <l>And taken to thy ſelfe a Sauiours name?</l>
               <l>If not to quell the rage of helliſh powers,</l>
               <l>And laſtly by thy death to redeeme ours.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If now (wo worth the while) thou ſhouldſt giue o're,</l>
               <l>And leaue thy worke ſo neere an happy end;</l>
               <l>Who then (ah who) ſhall promiſd health reſtore</l>
               <l>To vs, whoſe hopes on thee alone depend?</l>
               <l>No Sonne, but thou, of earthly mother bred,</l>
               <l>Hath power to cruſh the curſed Serpents head.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n outward ſhew
thou didſt pretend of late,</l>
               <l>An inward longing for this preſent time;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rging the Traitor to
accelerate</l>
               <l>The iſſue of his il-conceiued crime:</l>
               <l>Yet now the houre and <hi>Iudas</hi> both are nie;</l>
               <l>Thy courage failes, and thou art loth to die.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But oh! what haue I ſaid? can feare diſmay,</l>
               <l>Whom, mou'd to wrath, the earth doth quake to ſee?</l>
               <l>Can his thoughts change ſo ſoone, whoſe power doth
ſtay</l>
               <l>All powers in ſtable order as they be?</l>
               <l>Ah! no defects impaire not heauenly ſtore;</l>
               <l>And he is now the ſame he was before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſad eclipſing feare, that ſeemes ſo dimme,</l>
               <l>The glorious Sun-ſhine of his Deity,</l>
               <l>Could neuer haue a riſing cauſe from him,</l>
               <l>But from our natures imbecillity;</l>
               <l>Which, though ſupported by celeſtiall grace,</l>
               <l>Yet faintly ſhrinkes, and ſhewes of what it was.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>In what he hath aſſum'd our feeble fleſh,</l>
               <l>Therein he trembling faints, and ſtands diſmaid:</l>
               <l>Like as that ſtrength we haue in our diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Comes not of vs, but of his heauenly ayd:</l>
               <l>To right our cauſe, his Godhead ſuffers wrong:</l>
               <l>He weake by vs, and we by him are ſtrong.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>When firſt made <hi>Adam</hi> ioyleſſe all alone,</l>
               <l>In <hi>Edens</hi> beauteous Garden did remaine,</l>
               <l>To faſhion <hi>Eue</hi> he gaue his proper bone,</l>
               <l>And had with fleſh the place fill'd vp againe:</l>
               <l>So Chriſts deare-loued Spouſe the Church ſtill weares</l>
               <l>His rib of ſtrength, and he her frailty beares.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Retir'd about a ſtones caſt from the reſt,</l>
               <l>Hem'd in with horror, ſuch exceeding waight</l>
               <l>Of earth-committed ſinnes his ſoule oppreſt,</l>
               <l>That on both knees he fals, and after ſtraight,</l>
               <l>His paine increaſing, proſtrate lies to pray,</l>
               <l>That from him this ſad houre might paſſe away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ah, Abba, Father, which all things didſt make,</l>
               <l>And do'ſt preſerue them made, (if ſo may be)</l>
               <l>Bow downe thine eyes, and for thy mercy ſake,</l>
               <l>Remoue this bitter cup of wrath from me.</l>
               <l>Yet let not my will be fulfill'd herein,</l>
               <l>But thine (deare Father) which hath euer bin.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Full oft elſe-where good Chriſt did interceſſe</l>
               <l>For vs, and neuer had one ſute debar'd:</l>
               <l>And yet folliciting his owne diſtreſſe,</l>
               <l>Obtaines not of his Father to be heard:</l>
               <l>For God ſo lou'd the world, that now he gaue</l>
               <l>His onely Sonne from ſinne the ſame to ſaue.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Who Lambe-like mild in league with heau'ns decree,</l>
               <l>Folding earth-dwellers in as deare embrace,</l>
               <l>Would, pleading for himſelfe, repulſed be,</l>
               <l>That for vs praying, he might ſtill find grace.</l>
               <l>O rare obedience, perfect zeales true ſigne,</l>
               <l>How much owe we for this great loue of thine!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But now he riſeth from the dewie ground,</l>
               <l>To viſit his Diſciples left diſtreſt,</l>
               <l>And finds them all ſecurely ſleeping ſound:</l>
               <l>When waking <hi>Peter,</hi> (heauy as the reſt)</l>
               <l>O <hi>Simon,</hi> art thou now aſleepe? (quoth he)</l>
               <l>What? couldſt thou not watch one bare houre with me?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As he would ſay, Wert thou of ſelfe-accord,</l>
               <l>So prodigall of vowes, with timeleſſe ſpeed,</l>
               <l>And do'ſt ſo ſoone neglect thy helpleſſe Lord,</l>
               <l>In drowſie ſlumber at his greateſt need?</l>
               <l>Ill canſt thou in my ſafegard ſpend thy blood,</l>
               <l>That wilt not wake to do thine owne ſoule good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not ſo falſe <hi>Iudas,</hi> who for pettie gaine,</l>
               <l>Sleepes not a winke this night, nor can forbeare:</l>
               <l>Poſtes round the waked ſtreetes, cals vp his traine,</l>
               <l>Sollicits helpe, ſeekes armour euery where,</l>
               <l>Marſhals his Band himſelfe, and thinkes a yeere,</l>
               <l>Till he may come to apprehend me here.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O ſhame! that Satans ſlaues ſo forward are</l>
               <l>In acting miſchiefe, that ſhall bring damnation;</l>
               <l>And you, to ſaue your ſoules, deuoid of care:</l>
               <l>O watch and pray therefore, leſt ill temptation</l>
               <l>Oppreſſe your faith: the ſpirit faine would do it,</l>
               <l>But that weake fleſh is hardly brought vnto it.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not yet through-wak't, he leaues the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlumbring ſtil,</l>
               <l>And fraught with feares, departs againe to pray,</l>
               <l>Impulſt by weakneſſe of his humane will:</l>
               <l>O Father, if this cup in no wiſe may</l>
               <l>Paſſe by, vnleſſe the potion worke in me,</l>
               <l>Thy heauenly pleaſure let performed be.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus this good Shepheard, iealous of his ſheepe,</l>
               <l>Whom rauening Wolues, he knowes, will ſoone moleſt,</l>
               <l>Watches with care, whilſt they ſecurely ſleepe,</l>
               <l>And ſighes alone, that they in peace may reſt:</l>
               <l>Not ſparing to ingage his proper life,</l>
               <l>To ſaue them all from ſlaughtring butchers knife.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>His prayer ended, he returnes againe,</l>
               <l>And finds like comfort, that he found before:</l>
               <l>They ſtill ſlept hard, vnable to refraine</l>
               <l>One minutes reſt; and, which did grieue him more,</l>
               <l>So careleſſe of the former words he ſpake,</l>
               <l>Quite vnprouided what excuſe to make.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>O now what horror in this ſoule doth dwell?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aked of helpe,
forſaken all alone,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ught by his bloodie
foes, aſſail'd of hell,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>etraid, or elſe
neglected of his owne:</l>
               <l>Giuen vp by heau'n to die with painfull ſhame,</l>
               <l>And bare the burden of all ſinners blame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wake, my ſoule,
run forth with ioy and dread,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to this garden
where thy Sauiour lies;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ere ſhalt thou
ſee the Booke of life wide ſpred,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ith leſſons
ſtor'd of heauenly myſteries:</l>
               <l>There ſhalt thou ſee thy truth, thy ſtrength, thy
food,</l>
               <l>Thy way, thy life, thy light, and all thy good.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here ſhalt thou
ſee the way of patience,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Sun-bright lampe
of burning charitie,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he perfect patterne
of obedience,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he mirrour of
profound humility,</l>
               <l>The root of loue, the goale of vertues race,</l>
               <l>The ſalue of ſinne, and fulneſſe of Gods grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>here ſhalt thou
ſee the ſtrength of Iſraels weale,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>at valiant
<hi>Dauid,</hi> thy moſt louing God;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt to the fight,
arm'd all in fiery zeale,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rning with hot
deſire to ſpend his blood,</l>
               <l>And waſh away the foule opprobrious blot,</l>
               <l>That threats vile bondage, if he ſuccour not.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Emboldened with exceeding loue of thee,</l>
               <l>Here in theſe paled liſts alone he ſtayes,</l>
               <l>Expecting till his foes arriued be:</l>
               <l>Meane while accumulating ſundry wayes,</l>
               <l>With willing mind to his al-ready ſtore,</l>
               <l>Such paines, as neuer fleſh did feele before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O with what ſorrow did the nobler part</l>
               <l>Of his pure ſoule, where Reaſon hath her ſeat,</l>
               <l>Pity th'inferiour, where weake Senſe doth ſmart?</l>
               <l>How faithfully for it did he intreat,</l>
               <l>Vntill at laſt, concorded both in one,</l>
               <l>They ioyntly cride, Father, thy will be done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Yet though this bleſſed Vnion did gain-ſay</l>
               <l>Detract of time, whereto faint fleſh aſpires,</l>
               <l>From the Diſciples he departs away,</l>
               <l>And to his praying place againe
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</l>
               <l>And there the third time, doth with teares implore,</l>
               <l>Vſing like words as he had vſde before.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When lo, an Angel gliding through the ayre,</l>
               <l>Appeares to him, from ſtarrie Region ſent,</l>
               <l>Which makes him for a while deſiſt his prayer,</l>
               <l>To hearken what this heauenly Herald meant:</l>
               <l>Who nearer comes, with ſweet ſpeech comforteth</l>
               <l>His fainting Lord, againſt diſmay of death.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Sweet Ieſu, how art thou deiected now,</l>
               <l>From ſublime glory, to diſgrace and feare?</l>
               <l>Moſt true it is the Prophet ſpake, That thou</l>
               <l>Art ſomewhat lower made then Angels were,</l>
               <l>Since in thine agonizing languiſhment,</l>
               <l>To comfort thee, an Angel downe is ſent.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>See, ſee, O Angel, how thy Maker lies</l>
               <l>Below, and here on earth, afflicted ſore;</l>
               <l>Whom, plac't in maieſtie aboue the skies,</l>
               <l>With feare and reuerence you do all adore:</l>
               <l>Wonder of wonders, the like neuer done,</l>
               <l>How can thine eyes endure to looke thereon?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Can riuers adde vnto their fountaines ſlow,</l>
               <l>Through whoſe ſupply, thoſe ſtreames they haue, do
runne?</l>
               <l>Can branches helpe the quickning root to grow?</l>
               <l>Or pale-fac't Moone lend light vnto the Sunne?</l>
               <l>How canſt thou, Angel, comfort then his mind,</l>
               <l>In whom thy ſelfe doſt all thy comfore find?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>But this, O man, muſt needs on thee be laid,</l>
               <l>Whoſe fleſhes frailtie, and ſinnes earned ſmart,</l>
               <l>Doth with ſurcharging horror ſo inuade:</l>
               <l>That euen almoſt forgetting his beſt part,</l>
               <l>(His Godheads power) be ſdaines not in this dread,</l>
               <l>Of his owne creature to be comforted.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>And yet, alas, this comfort could not cure</l>
               <l>The death-ſicke dolours of his wounded heart:</l>
               <l>But now the time grew on, his body pure,</l>
               <l>Vnto the dreadfull Croſſe, muſt needes depart;</l>
               <l>And riſing vp, he thus to them did ſay,</l>
               <l>The man was neere, that ſhould their Lord betray.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No ſooner had our Sauiour told this newes,</l>
               <l>But ſtraight the traitorous <hi>Iudas</hi> with a
kiſſe,</l>
               <l>Betraid his Lord and Maſter to the Iewes,</l>
               <l>A cruell act, which loſt eternall bliſſe:</l>
               <l>The ſands on ſhore in number are not told:</l>
               <l>His ſundry faults paſſe number to vnfold.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>O let me breathe, before I do proceed:</l>
               <l>Surcharging loads will craue a little reſt:</l>
               <l>The grants are ſmall to them that ſtand in need,</l>
               <l>That will not bring ſome comfort to their breſt:</l>
               <l>And he that writes what doth in wicked lurke,</l>
               <l>Shall breathe him twice before he end his worke.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Looke how the Sea-fowles on a ſtormy day,</l>
               <l>Do flocke themſelues about the Ocean ſhore;</l>
               <l>As thicke as Leaues when Summer fleetes away,</l>
               <l>So throng theſe Iewes vnto him more and more:</l>
               <l>Cruell reward! he ought to them good will,</l>
               <l>And they, like traitours, ſought his blood to ſpill.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:17600:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en from the Garden
they their Maſter brought</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the Prieſts
and Elders of their crue:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ey bore falſe
witneſſe, there his life they ſought.</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch cride, that death
ſhould be his onely due:</l>
               <l>Labouring (indeed) as much as in them lay,</l>
               <l>To take the Life of liues, their Lord away.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d then from thence
they drag'd him to his death:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en to the Croſſe
they nail'd his hands and feet:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en did they ſtop
their bleſſed Sauiours breath:</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en did they him with
ſcornefull titles greet:</l>
               <l>And now the Scripture true is brought to paſſe:</l>
               <l>For he amongſt the wicked counted was.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> now the houre of
death being fully runne,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e heauens were
darke, he to his Father cries;</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> God, my God, why
doſt thou leaue thy Sonne?</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d ending ſo, his
ſoule from bodie flies.</l>
               <l>A happy death, ſince death doth make vs liue:</l>
               <l>And bleſt be He, that bleſſed life doth giue.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
